Inexact repeating alarms. Infinitely better than exact repeating alarms, but
still far from ideal. The problem with any kind of repeating
alarm is that it's still polling your server to check
for updates. So the more frequently you poll, the fresher the
data you can display, but the higher the cost in
battery life. You can pull as frequently to conserve battery but
that just means your content will be stale for longer.
You could just let the user decide the update frequency themselves,
but then you lose the magic. If only there was
a better way. Is such a thing possible? Yes it
is. Google cloud messaging lets your server notify your app
directly when there's data ready to be downloaded. Or it
can even include the new data in the message payload
itself. Using Google Cloud Messaging, you can send messages from
your server to any installed instance of your app via
the Google Cloud. As a result, you can stop polling,
which will immediately improve battery life and also improve the
freshness of your app. And instead, rely on your server
notifying clients when there's data to sync. These messages can
be simple tickles, that trigger a sync adapter by notifying your
app that there is new data or need to download.
Or you can include the new data within the message payload.
In the sunshine example, we're using someone else's server. But
even then, it may make sense to create your own middle
tier that pulls the source and notifies your installed app instances
when it notices a change. Now we're not going to set up a
server in this lesson, but you can see the full details for
using Google cloud messaging from the developer guide linked to instructor nets.